the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
all right everyone welcome to the
stowawa
i'm peter lindberg the steward of the
stoa and the stoa
is a place for us to cohere and dialogue
about what matters most at the nice edge
of this very moment
and today is thanksgiving here in canada
i'm from toronto canada
um so i'm going to invite everyone in
the chat to start
uh just write something down that you're
thankful for in this very moment
and while people are writing in the chat
i will share what i'm thankful for
i am thankful for this community
this strange community called the stoa
that's surrounded with
people who are not following a script
and
are co-writing the story together
um it's beautiful and i'm very grateful
for it
so today uh
we got danish mochtenberger sensemaker
in residence for
the month of october uh and this is a
digital porch
so there's no gender or theme we're just
gonna come sit on the the
digital stola and then ask daniel some
questions
and yeah there's a spreadsheet too uh
let's just see here i think someone
shared it already for people who just
came in
uh anybody wants to take notes just
start taking notes
um we're gonna have uh this is 90
minutes and after this and the same link
tyson wagner is going to do a rap on
battles which will explain what that is
at the end so if you want to
do something interesting just hang on um
so yes like i said there's a digital
porsche we're just gonna stand in some
questions if you have any questions put
them in the chat box
uh i will call on you uh you'll mute
yourself ask it to daniel if you don't
want to be on youtube indicate that i'll
read the question on your behalf
and as daniel said in the the first
question you know he can talk about all
this kind of like
sense making type issues and everything
in different platforms but feel free to
get personal
have some kind of uh um questions that
are you know localized to
what's going on in your world that might
be related to other people as well
an example like hannah um when daniel
came a couple weeks ago hannah
robbins talked about um anxiety attacks
that she had and daniel gave some
excellent advice
so you know feel free to go there and um
i'll curate the questions and
have a bias towards those um so
that being said uh i will allow
everyone to unmute themselves daniel how
are you doing today my friend
good i'm happy to be here the last time
was fun
and uh yeah i enjoy this opportunity to
just kind of be with the questions that
are actually alive and interesting for
people
and so i kind of wanted to start to
check in with you um
if there's any kind of questions or
concerns that are alive for you right
now
maybe related to the project you're
working on or something personal
that us at the stoa could reflect on
uh maybe stay with for a bit which in
turn can serve sort of as a like a
looping effect
that might inspire us to ask certain
questions or make comments which assist
you in your thinking whatever
is alive so i'll throw that as the first
question
there's certainly things with regard to
project we're working on that could use
help of people who are interested in
helping and that would be an interesting
thing to
come to later but um
i don't really want to go in a project
or tactical direction
to begin with i will say something that
was on my mind as i was coming into this
session today
um i was reading your
letter on that you posted of the
chess moves and thinking about some of
the questions
on power last time and
i don't know if there are more questions
that people have asked in that direction
but there was something that i wanted to
share
kind of about that is
i think it gets very easy
when we start saying if those who are
focused on the commons long term don't
learn how to be
effective at making things happen within
current environment then they won't be
effective and so there's a need to learn
influence power etc i think it's
it's easy for that to be a slippery
slope into getting captured by
moloch and justifying a bunch of um
unconscious ego things very quickly and
most people it actually wouldn't really
benefit them to have more power because
they don't have particularly clear
ideas on how to solve anything to begin
with um
and so you have to say like is there a
problem that i understand well enough
and have some solutions that really need
to be implemented where the key
thing is better capacity to
implement and most people don't have
that much power
over their own self meaning that much
coherence between the parts of
themselves
and so i would say like as far as power
literacy
learn how to have power in your
relationship with the facebook feed
and with food and with
the various things that you want
regarding the allocation of your own
attention and time
first and once there is some
significant capacity to actually
control your own attention
then you can start thinking about um
power literacy more
otherwise i think it's largely a wrong
order of operations
a focus
um so sovereignty comes to mind uh
and i'm curious uh how you wrestled
with becoming more sovereign in your
life and
maybe when you were doing the
psychotherapeutic work what kind of
common themes and advice did you give
for people to become more
sovereign
number one time i mean
there's a lot of different answers to
that right there's
everything from a meditation practice
where you
just choosing to do it regularly at all
involves a certain kind of
um commitment and discipline
and to be able to uh
control your thoughts to increasing
degree
if you're doing a concentration style
meditation to be able to control your
body to
not scratch the itch to notice it and to
not scratch it like
these are a lot of ways to be able to
notice impulses
and not have to automatically act on
them and
i mean cold showers and ice baths where
you consciously relax your body when it
wants to contract there's a lot of
places to be able to bring
unconscious or automated processes under
increasing
volition and then there's the inquiry
into where do the
where do the compulsive addictive
patterns come up the most
and is there some conditioning or trauma
or whatever underneath that that needs
work through
so there's a lot of answers but the one
i was about to start saying is i
remember one time
i got into um
you know really looking at addiction and
kind of addiction recovery
ideas in my early 20s and so
i didn't have anything that people would
normally call an addiction
meaning there was nothing that was
really not overeating or drugs or sex
relationships or anything that was
really damaging my life but i wanted to
look at
uh damaging my life in a
um really overt way but i wanted to look
at all the places where there was
compulsion
where i would routinely do something
that
was not aligned with my highest choice
executive function for myself and values
for myself
and i identified like
30 different things that had that were
subtle forms of addiction
um from relationship with food
to um
exaggerating stories to sound cooler
when talking to people and then
afterwards being like [ __ ] why did i do
that it wasn't overtly lying but it was
embellishing and then looking at what is
underneath that the
food thing would often times happen like
what are the triggers happens when
lonely or bored or whatever so
what are the ways of dealing with that
the embellishment thing has insecurity
underneath it
and um so just inventory
all of the places where behavior is
being compelled
more than it is being clearly chosen and
then looking at why
and how to work with that and there is
some
patience required in that process
because it can be very painful to notice
how
much we are actually
not volitional and yet a lot of
reactions to that make us less
volitional
um so if i go into like feeling really
depressed about that that i choose to go
into feeling really depressed or was
that also an automated
thought and emotional reaction um was
that reaction
at all helpful or aligned with the
things that i care about
and for me the idea
of
not actually having volition to be able
to be more aligned with what was
meaningful to me
was more painful than anything else
that's not true for everybody we have
different things that kind of move us
but the idea that there are some kind of
just automated
um patterns that would predict my
behavior in my life
was just such a dreadful idea that i
really wanted to
be able to notice wherever those
occurred and at least be able to stop
and then say if i wasn't being
controlled by some patterns what would i
choose and then that gets into the
existentialism of what is my basis for
choice
and what is fundamentally meaningful and
why those kinds of things
were you always so clear on what was
most meaningful
for you um and was it like the
articulation of it i imagine it changed
throughout the years and
how did you do you have like a system or
mechanism in place that updates it
there's a long time where
my felt sense of what was meaningful
and my cognitive understanding of
the existential basis for meaningfulness
writ large or objectively or something
like that
um would come into
conflict and
there was a point at which that got
resolved um
because i whenever i would see an
animal hurt in front of me i didn't have
to ask any questions about
meaningfulness to just
be completely clear that i wanted to
help them
or when i would see a person in need or
hurting there was a
there was an eminent or an embodied
sense of meaningfulness that was prima
facie
but then in being able to reflect on it
and say well why is
why is that thing meaningful and the
answer is something else well why is
that thing meaningful and
uh and which always gets into a question
about
big bang and the second law of
thermodynamics and whatever um
i and and fundamental
randomness and determinism i would get
uh challenged
so one thing that i remember really
helped me was starting to recognize the
actual eminent felt sense
of meaningfulness and purpose beyond my
understanding of it
i remember there was a quote by somebody
i don't know who it was
i think it was misattributed to rilke
that said
the heart knows reasons that reason
knows nothing of
and i uh
thurman i think and i thought about
and reflected on how kind of true that
was for me
and then oh it was um
joseph campbell said something to the
effect is paraphrase
that uh searching for the meaning of
life
is what we do when we are disconnected
from the actual experience of the
meaning of life
um but what people are actually seeking
for is a feeling of aliveness
and that very few people when they
actually feel actively engaged in life
or
asking the existential question around
its meaningfulness
it wasn't until later that i got in the
girdles and completeness theorem
and tarsky's incompleteness of formal
logical systems
and started to be able to make sense of
what that meant
with the first verse of the tao te ching
to be able to get that
ace
i wasn't going to have a semantic
framing of the meaningfulness of all of
reality that was somehow
outside of reality and could ground it
um
and so
logic is able to understand the bounds
of logic both the utility of it and the
bounds
of it um so i think the question is was
it always clear to me
experientially yes and cognitively
i was progressively trying to uh
find coherence between my intellectual
understanding and my
experience
awesome all right let's pivot to the
chats this
is going crazy right now okay uh do uh
you had a question
on uh children you're gonna mute
yourself and ask them to daniel
are you there do yep yep okay i'm here
can everyone hear me
sounds good so daniel um thanks for
being here
my questions uh i wanted to know what
are your thoughts about having children
and you know given how hard it is to be
happy even in the best
of circumstances you know being in a
first world country
having all the financial resources
being relatively safe um
you know that plus excess and it's
really difficult to be happy
plus the existential risk that you
bring up plus you know like the
resources needed to raise
kids you know and the opportunity cost
to use those resources to help other
people
how can one justify
having a baby or bringing a life into
existence
uh you know am i just a depressed
anti-natalist
for asking that question thank you
yeah i i think that's an increasingly
common question
um
and i don't have anything like a an
algorithm for how to answer if you
should have children or not across the
board
um i can tell you a few considerations
that come to mind
for me
and it's tricky because there are
considerations that are a bit
conflicting
there's at the
micro level of the way i would answer it
if we weren't thinking about population
and resource issues
and future catastrophic risk and the
opportunity cost of what
the person who's a parent could be doing
with their time and just focused on
their own learning and quality of life
and experience
versus kind of a macro way of answering
it and they're both important
there are plenty of people that are just
bad parents and being a parent doesn't
make them
grow up all that much but in in general
becoming a parent is the most
emotional maturity developing thing for
people
um and that doesn't mean that can't
happen other ways
but if someone is a if someone really
wants to be a good parent and they are
a thoughtful committed person
there's a bunch of things that happen
they start putting someone else
the consideration of someone else in
front of themselves because they don't
want to wake up in the middle of the
night to feed the baby but the baby
needs fed
and so there is a movement out of young
person
childish narcissism being the center of
the universe thing that starts to happen
that is extraordinarily maturing and
valuable for people
and then there's thinking about this
little person
developing into a person and who they're
going to become and what their
what is nature and what is nurture and
how they're being conditioned
that has people start to reflect on
their own conditioning and
how would i want this child to grow up
and where am i
not aligned with it where would i want
them to be different than me and then
can i actually help them be different
than me based on what i said are they
going to imprint
watching who i am so how do i have to
actually become
more to be the kind of parent i want to
be i watch people
grow a lot and then i'm more invested in
the future
because i really care about something
that is going to live beyond me so i get
more invested in the future
and how do i create and leave a better
place for them and start to have
long-term thinking
so there's a lot of very good things
that can happen
for someone's mental emotional
philosophical spiritual growth
and becoming apparent and things that
can actually
make them a better citizen because being
aligned with a longer-term future and
being a better citizen
can be very aligned
that said there's plenty of people who
uh have kids who don't spend that much
time thinking about how to become
how the way that they are in their being
is influencing this child and aren't
that philosophically
reflexive or that disciplined or have
that much time allocated
and um
it's always tricky because most any
who grew up with say parents who didn't
want to be parents or who were absent or
whatever
is still like well i'm glad they chose
to have me because i'm glad that i'm
here
right and i went through whatever
difficult processes
and had the person not been born
had the parents not chose to have kids
they there wouldn't be a person saying
i'm really bummed that i'm not here
right like it's always
easy no matter which path we go down to
say i'm glad that we chose that path
um
so i have chose not to have kids
and
well aware of
the developmental possibilities in being
a parent
and well aware of being able to
help develop uh people
that can be not just happy people but
also good citizens
um into the future
uh i had a very strong
paternal instinct since i was young
and i was and a lot of people have this
thought and most people grow out of it i
didn't
um where i was
aware of how many people and how many
animals and how much life was
unstewarded untended and
i felt the calling
to have that paternal instinct
and drive tend to the life that
currently exists that is untended
rather than bring new life because for
me the way
i would want to be a father
involves a amount of focus and
dedication and time
that like there is a real opportunity
cost on time
i think people have different callings
i've seen some people
like i said do better work in the world
and become more efficient and
uh when they have kids
i think uh i think caring capacity-wise
the planet would be better off with a
lot less people than we currently have
that is not me promoting eugenics or
catastrophe it's just saying
we're utilizing resources faster than
the reproduction rate of the resources
currently
i think that we see that while there has
been a lot of concern about
overpopulation we also see that japan's
birth rate
and some nordic countries birth rate
became sets
the populations actually start declining
and some people get concerned of a
collapse in population
i think collapse in population matters
for the current economic system but it
doesn't actually matter
for civilization unless we're talking
about massive infertility
because otherwise there will be
correction dynamics
and the economic system that was
predicated upon and needs continuous
population growth
has to end that's not a long-term viable
economic system
um so what would i say about having kids
there's obviously a default impulse to
just reproduce
that every animal has
i don't think that's a good enough
reason to be the best choice for how to
live a life and to have kids in the
current context
so rather than the default assumption of
uh
i'm going to go to school i'm going to
get a job i'm going to get married i'm
going to have kids and it's like that's
just
the thing that plays out i think if you
if someone feels that it is essential to
their dharma to raise
the future generations of civilization
that they're
that they feel a profound calling in
that way they're very called to
childhood development theory they're
thinking about
what would be a conscious enlightened
way to raise people
they are called to family and creation
of family and community
if someone feels that it's central to
their dharma then they should do that
and if they don't then i would like to
see what they do feel essential to their
dharma
and then answer other things in light of
that
here's my initial thoughts
any follow-up question due no that's not
thank you very much
tyler you got a question on psychedelics
you're going to mute yourself
okay uh since we must escape from
algorithm manufactured realities in
order to do proper sense making
and since we must change our
relationship to each other the world
and ourselves to move from game a to
game b
uh what role do psychedelics have to
play in this transition
from personal experience i even find if
i'm micro dosing i find it much easier
to put my phone away and recognize it as
a stupid damaging thing
so i was just i know the answer is
something but i was just wondering what
you had on that
it feels like a couple different
questions put together
because psychedelics can obviously have
a role as they have
historically or plant medicines before
an algorithmically mediated digital
environment
and there are answers to the algorithm
digital environments that don't
necessarily involve psychedelics so
there's
how do we uh how do we deal with
hypernormal stimuli
is kind of one question uh what is the
therapeutic developmental evolutionary
role of psychedelics and then is there
an intersection between those two
questions
um if i
let's talk about hypernormal stimuli
first
i have noticed that people who
chronically are checking their phone
looking for notifications
don't at burning man and burning man's
obviously its own hyper-normal stimuli
but not just at burning man they don't
when they're camping with friends um
if they're in an environment where
that's closer to the evolutionary
tribal type environment that we
developed in where there's kind of a
rich field of human interaction
they're less susceptible to addiction at
large
one of the things that i think about
hyper normal stimuli
is that we're more susceptible to them
in a hyper normal environment of the
healthy evolutionary
stimuli that makes a healthy
human social primates so when people
have more contact with nature that's
bringing them into
all of their senses not just a kind of
2d screen when they have more contact
with other
people um i see that there
they go they're called to go to the
fridge and just look at what's in there
less often they're called to scroll the
phone less often
governor mate's work on that the biggest
predictor for
addiction is how lonely someone is and
the biggest kind of anti uh predictor
for addiction is the
depth and connectedness of the
relational field i think there's
something very deep to this
um so that's not the entirety of
the answer of how do we deal with
hypernormal stimuli but i think a lot of
hypernormal stimuli
is
an impulse to fill a certain kind of
emptiness
that most people's modern life has
and um i think it's why there's so much
call for people wanting to move to
communities
and back to the land type movements and
things like that um
so i think that we need to develop some
resilience
capacities to hypernormal stimuli in
addition but the foundation of it is do
i actually have a healthy
full life of the types of stimuli that
make a healthy human being
now psychedelics can obviously bring you
more into your
senses and into kind of rich experience
where in the fullness of that kind of
rich experience you're on the mushrooms
and the tree looks way more beautiful
and the sky looks way more beautiful
that there's less of the kind of
wanting some dopaminergic hit that the
notification will give you
um
i'm i'm not really oriented to a future
where
somebody needs to be continuously on
psychedelics even micro doses to
have enough uh presence that they aren't
susceptible to
hypernormal stimuli though um
now what is the role of psychedelics
we'll answer just kind of that other
question i would say the role of
psychedelics i'll describe as a
subset of the role of state induction
processes
that's not the only thing they can do
when you're micro dosing it it's not
necessarily state induction but for the
most part
if you kind of think in an uh integral
psychology term in terms of the
difference between
state induction and stage development
and kind of shadow integration um
can induce experience but that are
temporary right they can induce very
profound states then they're going to go
away then the question is
what is the persistent or lasting role
of that state
and that is meaningful and if there
isn't some developmental process to
integrate that state into stage it can
actually become kind of addictive
um if the only way i have to have an
experience
of the beauty of life or the numinous or
great insights through psychedelics and
i don't
it doesn't start to become more of my
baseline or have other ways of getting
it
then i probably need to do psychedelics
all the time
um so i think psychedelics or
breath work like holotropic type breath
work or
um tantric type processes that use
sexuality as a method of state induction
i think the state induction can be very
powerful
if it's part of a more integrated human
development process
so the psychedelic assisted
psychotherapy where you're for instance
some of the way that uh trauma work has
been done with mdma
where uh if someone's chemistry works
with mdma well
they kind of chemically go into a place
uh where they kind of can't feel bad
right they feel so good at an
experiential level
then let's say they have a ptsd trigger
about something every time they thought
about that thing they feel really bad
so now we the person's on mdma and
they're getting facilitated to go think
about that thing that always makes them
feel bad and they can't even access
feeling bad now but a new neurological
association is happening with feeling
this kind of
blissful ecstatic state and thinking
about this previous situation
where the next time because we know
memory consolidation
is that we don't remember the original
thing we remember the way it has been
reconsolidated each time we remember it
and the kind of pavlovian association
can change
then the next time i think about that
thing i don't have the same immediate
set of trauma patterns that are
associated um
sometimes in like a single session
someone can have a
enduring change with that kind of work
i had a in in my exploration with
psychedelics i had a general rule that
i would have some clear intention
whether it was a
ayahuasca journey or a peyote journey or
whatever
and then as soon as i would start to
come
down from the experience where i was
still altered but i was
capable of thinking in full sentences
and writing i would start writing
and i would start writing all the
insights because what i found
was especially if you go into deep
journeys the states are so
different that like dreams you kind of
end up losing most of it like you can't
even remember
most of the actual what did that feel
like and most of the details and the
insights
and so like dreams if the moment it's
there you capture it
you can start to build a bridge between
your normal state and that state by
being able to access the content of the
dream or the psychedelic state in your
normal consciousness you start to be
able to
to access it more so as soon as i would
start to come down from the journey i
would just start writing all the
insights and sometimes it was just
an insight about like what the world is
the beauty of it the nature of my
experience
sometimes it was specific insights about
philosophy or psychology or whatever
relationships and then
i would a couple hours later come back
and reread it
and as i was rereading it and i was now
coming down even further
i was experientially further away from
those experiences
but i was remembering them and i'm like
oh yeah and then what i would do is try
and re-feel what i felt
right and as i was writing i knew i'd be
coming back and rereading it so i was
setting this anchor
of really noticing what i felt
as i was describing it so i was kind of
linking a felt state to those words as i
was writing them so then i come back
and a couple hours later and then the
next day and the next day
and i remember how i felt when i was
writing it and remember how i felt when
i was in the
journey associated with it and so then i
had this kind of
that was a huge part of integration and
then i had this
uh general practice that whatever the
insights were
i would do the practices i needed to
integrate those before using that
medicine again
so i didn't just become dependent on a
bunch of external stimuli i was using
the external stimuli to gain
insights to then actually do development
work that became internalized
and um
so i think they can be extraordinarily
powerful
psychotherapeutic developmental tools
used rightly i think
they can be damaging you strongly like
any very powerful tool
um
if i go into
a so i'll give you a couple examples
if i go into a more neuroplastic state
one of the
ideas is that there's increased
plasticity
and so i can make new associations so
the psychotherapy or the learning can
happen
better if i go to an increased
plasticity state and have a really bad
trip and just kind of
um run a bunch of neural loops on some
very negative stimuli i can actually
come out kind of traumatized and i've
seen heaps of people do this
um and i did this
before i in my earliest experimenting
before i kind of knew better
um
and so this is another
thing is that the the experience itself
while on the psychedelic
or the empty agenda whatever you want to
call it ends up having less enduring
effect than
the meaning you make of it and how you
internalize it and how it ends up
changing behavior and practice and
so the meaning making process
is really key and a good facilitator
will
make a big difference to this so
um let's say somebody's on a
mushroom journey on a high dose and they
start having a very clear hallucination
of demons chasing them and they're
freaking out about demons chasing them
i've seen this many times
and someone uses a particular kind of
metaphysical interpretation
and i'm giving i'm actually quoting an
example of something i
i witness many times
someone gives an interpretation that
those demons are in the astral realm and
they really are chasing the person and
the mushrooms are helping that person
see into the astral realm
and it's because of bad things they did
in the past life so now in order to
fight that demon they need to have a
circle of salt and wear a feather and
whatever um
the person can come out believing in
demons in a natural realm and bad past
life stuff where now they
get scared any time that feather that
protects them isn't with them and
they're like thinking about demons
and they actually get messed up because
of the cognitive interpretation of the
experience
now let's say that same person's going
in they see the demon and
someone who has kind of an archetypal
symbolic
framework psychotherapeutic framework is
working with them
and says hey in this journey is arising
in your mind
is images in your mind and that can't
hurt you can't hurt you
so turn towards the demon rather than
run away from it
and ask it what it wants and they turn
towards the demon
and the demon that is scary becomes
their dad yelling at them when they were
a kid
and then they continue to be in dialogue
and then it becomes their dad
when he was a little kid being beat by
his dad and then they see a lineage of
past on trauma and they see how they've
embodied it
and now they have a meaning making that
is very different and they can actually
really
uh maybe walk away with a very empowered
set of changes so i think
um people having the right cognitive
frameworks
to interpret the experience is really
important
um and like i said i think it can be
damaging
if done wrongly um
i think the right medicines
the right dose the right pacing the
right set and setting the right
interpretation the right facilitation
all those things matter
cool any follow-up uh no
great thank you dana so uh
we'll pivot to dreams now uh
randy you had a question on dreams
hi can you hear me yep yep okay great
um so yeah this is perfect transition
from what you just said about uh
confronting the demons in your mind um
so i'll try to keep this brief um i'm
curious about the role that dreams might
have to play
in relation to problem solving
creativity and potentially to our
collective sense making practices
um so just to throw out a couple
stimulating tidbits
um have you heard the story of the
brilliant indian mathematician
born in 1887 he stated that the insight
for his work came to him and his dreams
on many occasions
uh ramanajan said that throughout his
life he repeatedly dreamed of a hindu
goddess known as
namakol she presented him with complex
mathematical formulas over and over
which he could then test and verify upon
awakening
similarly the melody to the beatles song
yesterday
came to paul mccartney in a dream he
woke up and stumbled at the piano by his
website to work out the chords
he says i just fell out of bed found out
what key i had dreamed it in and i
played it
and just to give a quick personal
example
i wasn't going to say this but what you
said about the the demons so when i was
like five years old i had a nightmare
um in which uh i encountered a monster
in a cave and i woke up and crying and
telling my brother about it he said if
that was me
i would have kicked that monster's butt
and wouldn't you know at the very next
night i had the same dream and i went
lucid i remembered what my brother had
said
and i confronted the monster and since
then dreams have always felt very
important to me i learned to tie my
shoes in a dream
okay so after all that um
i'll give you two questions one personal
one less personal
the first question is given that your
mind daniel
contains such rich detailed models of
reality
and the fact that you are so driven to
solve some of the world's most
perplexing problems
i'm curious if your dreams play any
conscious role in this process
have you ever done any lucid dreaming or
had any insights and a dream to problems
that you've been working on
or on a less personal note um are you
aware of or have you ever considered the
role
that shamanic dreaming aka lucid
dreaming
and the shared interpretation of dreams
could potentially play
either in therapy or perhaps even in
collective sense making
for example while lucid dreamings you
can face your fears phobias etc like i
mentioned
thank you for your patience and
listening to that i appreciate it
yeah when ramonagen um got kind of found
by littlewood and hardy and
the rest of math community uh a lot of
people got very interested and if they
could figure out how to have ramanujan's
dreams and
have dorgan come bring them um infinite
series math equations and
so far unfortunately nobody else seemed
to become ramanujan
um what made him develop that way and is
that developable
is a very interesting question um
i have done some dream interpretation
and lucid dreaming work not nearly as
much as many people have so
i'll say the few thoughts that come to
mind
um
if someone starts thinking about
something consistently enough
it's very common that they'll start
dreaming about it there's that whole
thing when you're learning a language
especially an immersion when you shift
to start dreaming in that other language
you have a sense of like okay now
there's actually a deep immersion
happening
someone who's playing chess all the time
will dream chess moves
um and so of course a musician who's
immersed in music or a mathematician
who's immersed in that
their subconscious is going to be
processing things that their conscious
mind is processing
and so the idea of
this is one of the things that um
actually in the startup world there's a
famous kind of
thinking about this which is um
people who are investing in a startup
and venture capitalists
want whoever's doing the startup to be
so focused on it that
they dream about it right that idea that
you have enough focus on this thing that
it is what actually
in engages all of your discretionary
creativity
and that sometimes means sleeping dreams
sometimes it means daydream sometimes it
means what pulls you out of reverie or
meditation or whatever it is
so there's definitely something to being
intensively enough focused
consciously that your other than
conscious mind is also processing
those topics um and
i have definitely had my life experience
whenever my focus becomes pretty intense
on a certain set of problem solving i
dream about those
that and will have you know interesting
kinds of insights
in the dream space i find that
the insights are for me
better in the thoughts that take me out
of meditation
so if i'm thinking about a problem and
then i go meditate
where i stop thinking about the problem
and i'm using a
breath or mantra or something that
clears mind then there'll be
oftentimes a solution to the problem i
was working on or an insight that kind
of emerges out of that quietness
but i'll remember more of it because i'm
not transitioning from
a sleep state but i know some people who
practice lucid dreaming a lot who have
that same experience there but i would
call these similar right they're just
altered states of consciousness where
the other than conscious mind gets to
process the stuff the conscious mind has
been processing
um i and
when we look at scientists who have
dreams like the snake biting its tail
giving the inside
to the benzene ring or a monogen or
whatever
there's really never stories like that
where the people were not fully
engrossed thinking about the thing who
had the insights
um
so there was a talk once
between the dalai lama and eckhart tolle
on this topic
and i'm only vaguely remembering it but
it was something to the effect of
somebody asked
i think eckhart
when you access the power of now
whatever you want to call it when you
access present silence
um do you have the ability to do
anything coming out of that space that
that's a space where kind of all
possibilities reside
um like could you get the kind of math
that einstein would get in his reverie
and that both eckhart and the
dalai lama agreed that despite all of
their meditation they never got math
they never got physics and they didn't
get the ability to kick
the um key soccer
play but the soccer player who takes a
moment and drops into deeper presence
does kick better than if they don't drop
into presence and so does the
mathematician that it's basically
taking the input that that being has
into a state that processes the input
differently
which can then give new outputs
from that kind of input um
i did some study of psychics and
channels in my early 20s
and what i found was that when i asked
them
objectively true and false questions
like somebody's social security
number and things like that that the
channel or or math questions or
chemistry questions it should be true
universally the pleiadian should know or
whatever
akashic records should have but where
the channel had never been exposed to
that knowledge
they never got it right um not one time
in hundreds of times asking it but that
didn't mean it was pure gibberish
oftentimes these people
when they were talking to someone about
their family or divorce or life said
profoundly insightful things the
person's like how the [ __ ] did you know
that
and the way that i interpreted it
was their degree of insightfulness was
proportional
to one how much experience they had of
that domain
so if they've paid attention to humans
and relationships their whole life and
really kind of paid attention they have
a
pattern matching capability for
something that they have a lot of
pattern
around and then it was also proportional
to
how much they could let go of their
assessment models and go to an other
than
conscious place where you've got kind of
conscious these pieces of data these
axioms these logical steps rational
process then you have other than
conscious
lots of bandwidth i just took in a set
of inputs and now my other unconscious
mind is pattern matching this across a
whole bunch of stuff and something pops
out so you get an
intuition that seems to be a aha out of
nowhere
and so when the person would ask the
pleiadians a question or ask the angels
a question or
whatever it was they were going into a
quiet receptive place
that was whatever the cognitive
mechanism they needed to use was
and so what i would find is that they
would actually do good pattern matching
and they would
say to the person in front of them more
often than statistically random
such and such is happening for you
you're going through a divorce or this
then the person like how the [ __ ] did
you know and it's like well
there are patterns across people who are
going through similar experience this
person has
been with tens of thousands of people in
their life they're
they're kind of getting a gestalt and
then there's a pattern recognition on
that gestalt
so i think intuitive space meditation
space
dreaming space that kind of process can
happen
um so i i'm not saying that it is
accessing things from the akashic record
i'm saying that it is accessing things
from our own mind brain
being through different processing a
different kind of processing that takes
those inputs and
processes them differently now am i
positive that no one accesses things
from the akashic record no of course not
it's a kind of an unfalsifiable
proposition but i don't have any
evidence to believe it either
the other thing i'll say about dreaming
is
i don't think it's very i don't think
it's good
to think in terms of dream
interpretation
that a particular dream interpretation
model is true
like objectively that snakes always mean
this and water means
this and whatever or that everyone in
the dream
in the jungian sense is an aspect of you
like
sometimes that's the right model
sometimes it's not sometimes the dream
is clearly just kind of a smorgasbord of
gibberish of whatever stimuli you had
that day sometimes it feels
like it's processing old trauma or
whatever it is
so with dream interpretation i think
rather than say
what did the dream mean as if it has an
objective meaning
for you to say did this interpretation
give me insight
was the interpretation clarifying
insightful useful
if so awesome and sometimes i've seen 10
different interpretations all be
insightful
so if you take it as fodder for a
inquiry process where the real benefit
is happening through your own inquiry
and that is
that's a starting point i think that can
be quite valuable
in the same way that i think uh tarot
can be valuable
if you take it that the cards are being
magically pulled for a specific reason
and that they mean
a specific thing it's going to be
nonsense
but if you take the cards as
representing archetypes that you can
interpret a million different ways which
happens right
in different contexts the same tarot
reader is interpreting that card in a
different way
and so you're really using them as
archetypes for the exploration of
something to see what fits
i think there's a lot of things like
that that can be
sources of insight but one needs to be
kind of grounded in how they're
processing it
and last thing on the lucid dreaming the
intentional
bringing things into dream space and
trying to develop some volition
i have friends that are very deep
practitioners of this
and do like have a lot of personal
growth and insight happen
in the space i've done some of it
um i won't go into what the practices of
how to lucid dream more effectively are
because that's
kind of common knowledge and well
written about but
i think lucid the things you can do in
lucid dreaming
and the benefit they can have for you
psychologically are a lot like
psychedelic assisted psychotherapy
possibilities
in the psychedelic assisted
psychotherapy i can see
like that demon feels very real in a
particular way
or i can visualize the event that
happened in my childhood or whatever it
was in a deeper richer way the same is
true in the dream space it's almost like
i kind of get to go into an immersive
experience
place in my psyche
and uh
so where somebody goes and confronts the
demon
like you were mentioning and sometimes
all that happens is they confront it and
the demon
dies or runs away but what that person
needed to do was learn how to stand up
and get courage
or they find out what the demon really
was it becomes them their own
self-criticizing voice or their dad or
their whatever it was
like really powerful insight and
healing can happen in that space
okay
and if anybody learns how to get
ramanujan's dreams to happen on
methodology then i want to take that
course
future session at the the stoa um
all right uh there's a culture war
happening in the chats right now
um some people want oh let's talk about
system change
let's talk about inner work and so uh
aaron is doing some medical mediation
with his question
uh so arnold if you can meet yourself
and ask your question to daniel
hi daniel thank you um yeah someone made
a comment
in the chat um that the session seems to
be
steering towards inner work instead of a
more kind of external
systems change uh and so i i
respond to that saying what is the
proper balance of
interim work and activism uh sort of the
internal
motivation for change and the external
motivation for change and
does one perceive the other
yeah that's a good question um and i
will just say for context
we can talk about um
whatever here and i think last time
there was a combination of
inner work and call it systems questions
um i don't really talk about
psychology or personal philosophy in
other public forums so i told peter i
was quite happy to have this one go in
more of a kind of
personal philosophy psychology
orientation because i don't really
um there are other forms where i do that
and i don't know if any
i mean it's kind of strange having
people ask me my thoughts on these and
i'm not an expert on
all these topics so i don't know if it's
useful but um
but answering the question of is there
an order of operations between personal
inner work
and um dharma
i think the
the right way to think about it is kind
of as a virtuous cycle or a reciprocal
process
where as i develop myself like my
obvious
capacity right my my cognitive
capacities to understand the problems my
social capacities to communicate
effectively towards
organization and problem solving my um
my psychological disposition to be
clear and not you know being
taken off by disruptions
obviously as i'm developing myself i
have more capacity
to do things in the world but it's also
true that as there are things in the
world i really want to do
it's the best motive to develop myself
and to develop myself in a
more focused less naval gazing way
and because if if i'm just wanting to
develop myself
because because i have some generalized
goal of enlightenment or whatever
it's endless right like i can keep
finding new little patterns that i have
and little traumas and areas to grow
forever
and um new states to reach a new
methods to inquire into and i stay
basically self-focused which is kind of
narcissistic
uh in its focus and oftentimes that
impulse is actually the expression
of it of trauma itself it's the
expression of i'm not good enough
and the way to become good enough
sometimes it's get really buff sometimes
it's get really rich
sometimes it's get famous sometimes it's
really do development work on myself
um or become really smart but it's
actually an expression
of i'm not enough coming out in that way
where you're actually
healing some things and doubling down on
the core trauma um
whereas if i have a sense of i'm gonna
die and all my development will kind of
not matter anymore
like i take my development with me when
i die right my
the things that i learn don't stay in
the field outside of
work that i produce in ways that i touch
other people and touch the world
so if my life is pretty short in
duration
but life is going to continue and
my life isn't the only thing meaningful
to me life with a capital l is
meaningful to me and my experience but
other people's experience is meaningful
then i want to say well in the short
time that i'm here what is it that i
really
care to how do i want to touch the world
that ripples on beyond
beyond me and scope to other people and
beyond my life and time
and as i really think about that and i
think about what actually is meaningful
to me what is sacred to me what
what is worth allocating the finite bit
of my life energy towards
then that that can inspire a kind of
development in dharma right uh
development and
a sense of meaningfulness purpose
mission
and capabilities but
also it will show me the personal work
that i need to do of what's in the way
of me being good at that
and so let's say i noticed that i'm
there's my work would be really
benefited by public speaking but i'm too
afraid of public speaking
but like what
i feel is mine to do here and that
matters to me in a way more than my own
life would be benefited by that then i
[ __ ] do the work to get over the fear
of public speaking
not just because of some generalized i'm
growing myself in all these different
ways
but because i'm not going to
let some
lack of skill or some trauma or some
disposition get in the way of me and
what i'm here for
and so there's a deeper motive and more
focus of
what to focus on if i find that
i can't actually empathize or tune in
with other people enough that they like
working with me so everybody
quits and i'm like okay there's
interpersonal work that i need to do
because otherwise i can't be effective
towards the things that matter to me
um so i think
ones focus on what they feel called to
contribute to
can be a context setting for
their own personal development in their
skills and their psychological work
and then of course as they grow in their
cycle
as they grow in their skills they start
thinking about the things that they
could do that they didn't even know they
could do before they had that skill
and as they grow in their psychological
work they have more insight about oh
that thing i
felt really called to do was actually me
just projecting my trauma on the world
um i needed to protect everybody because
i couldn't protect my mom when i was
little or my
kid sister or whatever it was and so
there's this reciprocal relationship
that as my skills develop as my own
internal awareness
develops and as healing occurs and as my
experience of trying to benefit what i
care about in the world develops
they can all inter-enrich each other
cool uh aren't any uh follow-up
there's always infinite follow-ups but
no that's it
thank you appreciate it great uh so
we're gonna go
uh with margaret then evan and amber so
margaret if you can unmute yourself
so my question is daniel do you have a
method for
organizing your mental architecture and
how do you personally store and access
various types of information and
memories
say a little bit more about the context
of the question
uh i'm curious to hear it's a question i
ask to many people i'm just curious if
uh i would assume everyone's mental
architecture is different and unique
i guess i'm curious about if you have a
process for how
you work with yours or restructure it as
necessary
as well as in this context you
are you know accessing a lot of
information about different subjects and
actively listening to the questions and
drawing out pieces of it and you're
managing to
weave together very complex answers
across many domains which i would guess
speaks to in part your experience in
investigating those domains but also
something that's happening within your
physical and mental structure
to allow for that like networking yeah
yeah
yeah i get the question now
so
having uh a knowledge and experience set
that is
very interconnected and um
very flexible in terms of what things
might be relevant what things might be
most relevant
because like for any of these questions
we
i could answer them 100 different ways
and you know we could take a very long
time so there's a question of like
and i don't know that i'm getting it
right but what
seems like the most relevant way for
this particular question in this
particular context and the amount of
time that makes sense
somebody asked me earlier today
whether they should go back to graduate
school or what the right process was
to learn better um analytical
skills and they they ended up asking
questions very much like this of
how do i learn many different analytical
processes and connect them together and
know which one to apply how to how to
know which epistemologies or
methodologies would apply well to which
domains
um are you saying that's not the
question
yeah that's not the question but i'm
happy to hear an answer to it
but yeah it's not the question but i i
think it's the answer might be related
um what i shared with him
is that um the learning process that
i mostly utilized
i mean i had some time where i um
took college courses and learned like
fixed curriculum
but even when i did that when i was
taking in the curriculum i was
thinking about how the knowledge in
whatever field related to everything
else that i
knew and how i would apply it and how i
would apply it to all different kinds of
problem sets
but for the most part my study happened
in the context of trying to
figure out specific problems i was
interested in
that so the example that i gave him
because he had been interested in
like what actually happened in 911 which
is a very interesting and tricky
research topic
and i said so if i was studying that
you would see a group like architects
and engineers for 911 truth talking
about
uh the temperature of jet fuel and the
melting temperature
of steel but i would need to get into
what kind of steel so
there's some metallurgy i would need to
learn and there's some kind of
construction structural engineering
around the kinds of steel that went in
there and the temperature of weld joints
and
um and then is it a there's some kind of
thermodynamics in chemistry regarding
jet fuel of does it always burn at the
same temperature
or what if i have a strong kind of
chimney effect or draft so there's like
a bunch of different domains and then
the impact of the plane there's like
classical mechanics that i need to do to
be able to factor that and
how would that correspond to richter
scale for how the
building was designed to be able to
impact stuff and
and then thinking about the claims of
what norad was doing that day or what
the cia knew what the fbi knew that it'd
be like do i actually understand
how the branches of government work and
what each of those groups do and how
they're connected
so my study would be there's a topic i
want to figure out and
if i really pay attention to as i'm
trying to make sense of it what other
people are referencing i actually don't
know most any of what they're talking
about like i don't know that
the metallurgy i don't know the burning
temperatures i don't know the structures
of government well enough to know if
norad said that versus strategic air
command what that means
so i would just it all seemed relevant
it all seemed interconnected and
relevant
because otherwise i'm like okay well
i'll just take their word on that and i
really don't know what i'm talking about
but now i'm building
a logical model based on something i
don't really know what i'm talking about
and so then i would go down wikipedia
rabbit holes or
whatever in encyclopedias or university
sites i would find to try to study that
stuff
and i wouldn't actually have to make a
rigid taxonomy
because it was connecting based on
authentic curiosity and i was thinking
through
how all these things connected so there
was a natural kind of synaptic
taxonomy that occurred where everything
was connected to everything else through
the process of even how it was being
studied
and then what happened was those same
topics were just as
flexibly interconnectable not in that
initial point of inquiry but now in the
other point of inquiry because
everything i learned happened that way
um so i think how someone is
learning originally is are there these
separate subjects with clear divisions
or is there the study of how reality
works and the interconnectivity between
all the domains
so i think it wasn't until later in life
i started
thinking in formal taxonomies and
taxonomy theory
and where a kind of bottom-up folksonomy
or where a top-down taxonomy works best
different ways of taxonomizing things
and why those would be useful
and then there were meta
uh there were meta taxonomies based on
deeper ontology
um this was actually something that uh
specifically
forest eminent metaphysics created a
formality for me that i had not had
before
was this idea in the metaphysics that
any
of a way of defining a domain of inquiry
what the boundary of inside and outside
the domain are
and then the three axioms that there are
these three orthonormal ontological
bases
in each one and that there's a
relationship between those
between those ontological
axes that are defined by those axioms
and so then when i'd be looking at any
domain i'd be converting it
into that as a kind of meta ontology
just like some people do with integral i
just integral just
much less formalized and so i i kind of
got into different meta-ontological
models
that was the most formal and fundamental
one i found
and then that took the organic way i had
learned
and started reifying and allowing me to
navigate it more
precisely and consciously
and even just like i like taxonomies
just even formal ones knowing everything
that's wrong with them
i like being able to take a paper before
writing it like typically if i'm working
with a team and they're going to write
something i always ask them to do an
outline first
to see are we clear on the main concepts
before we flush them out the questions
or whatever i like to tackle these
questions but i also know that i could
do that taxonomy a bunch of different
ways do i have three fundamental
categories do i have five
what is the benefit and damage of doing
it different ways
so there was also just playing with
mappings
of different kinds of taxonomies and
being
and this is where it's like no models
true they're all useful
where then i became very unattached to
any particular taxonomical models but
quite comfortable with being able to use
them and do mappings between them
so my i guess what i'm hearing
is that
this is not like i guess i was trying to
ask questions about direct information
encoding
and i'm hearing that your chosen
method is using these taxonomies and
meta-ontological models in order to
map that information to domains which
then have connections and can be
restructured at will
yes do you mean more like how do i
actually store information on my
computer
well your your human computer perhaps or
like whatever you may view as your
consciousness and mind
yeah i think the answer i gave is the
is the clearest answer but if there is a
follow-up question on the part i didn't
address let me know
that's good for you thank you thank you
so i got a follow-up question on like
cognitive organization
um how do you get [ __ ] done like like
what's your time management
system and how do you negotiate between
all the [ __ ] you have to get done
in orientation to what is most
meaningful
um you want me to do like
productivity principles basics
that i find useful sure um like could be
anything from getting things done by
david allen anything that you apply or a
bespoke system that you use that you
think is could be generalizable
yeah i did uh
david allen and franklin covey
and tony robbins uh time of your life
system and a bunch of those and they're
all like there's valuable stuff in all
of them
um the david allen kind of
brain dump everything in a place that
you'll keep coming back to so your mind
doesn't keep looping the thing to
kind of free up cognitive space that's
super valuable um
i'll tell you i'll tell you a few of the
kind of
productivity practices that i actually
use regularly which is different than
all the ones that i know that i don't
end up actually using regularly but
probably would be good if i did um
i'm i make sure in my
work that i have very clear outcomes
so i i know the theory of it right i
know the philosophy i know the values
but then
it comes down to clear outcomes at a
particular time
and the outcomes that i'm responsible
for are less than five
usually three but never more than five
so they're
everything has to chunk that way so that
i don't have to go reference it to look
those up those those can be clear and
top of mind like i know
the outcomes that i'm moving forward
towards and then
every possible call or engagement or
email
has to be in light of which of those
outcomes is it moving forward
and is it the most effective thing i can
do
to move that outcome forward and
then of course when one of those
outcomes is completed and a new one
emerges
like the five can change and they should
change over time
but that's one thing
and then there is a
above the line practice that i actually
find quite useful
which is towards the one or two or three
outcomes that is most
meaningful critical timely and leveraged
current today
um there's one to three things that i am
for sure going to get done before i go
to sleep
that are the highest leverage things
towards that and then there might be 50
other things on my to-do list that i'd
like to get done that are below the line
where i make sure i get the above the
line ones done first
there's a few things that does it
actually allows someone to be able to
rest when they need to rest
because they know the thing that they
really needed to get done got done
then and as opposed to the general sense
that
i never got enough done um
and it makes sure that the highest
leverage things get first priority
and make sure that you're thinking about
priority clearly enough
um also if i
say i have 20 to do items that have come
in through
conversations i had with the team and
conversations with external people and
emails and whatever and they're chunked
under an outcome
it doesn't automatically mean i look
through those 20 and put them in
descending order of which one's most
important towards the outcome there
might be a way to move the outcome
forward that's more effective than any
of those
so i look at all those to make sure i
know what they are i look at the
consequence of not doing them in a time
that was
said but i also give myself some time to
think about
strategically is there a higher leverage
thing i could do to move that outcome
forward
in designing these i do use theory of
bottlenecks
of saying for the overall project to
succeed what are the bottlenecks
and then is there an order of operation
of the bottleneck sometimes there's
more work to do than the team can do and
human resources are really a bottleneck
i need more people
and sometimes capital is the thing that
is the bottleneck to that i need to
raise money to be able to
get those people on and maybe the
bottleneck to that is i need to put some
uh fundraising materials together so i
get very clear like fundraising
materials close
funds but i'm closing funds for people
so i
know exactly how much funds i need and
don't keep raising beyond that
to then start to get the people on um
and which people first
so um
theory of bottlenecks and also just
general considerations of leverage
which things that i do leverage the
existing team
and other people's work and the rest of
my work more effectively
that's all just kind of like strategy
and planning but then the tactics is
things like
making sure that it's not too many
categories at once
for a given month or quarter and that
you're clear for that particular day
um daily planning is obviously not
enough because you need to book
appointments
and so you're also going to be looking
at kind of weekly and monthly planning
and having some regular process
to do that planning aligned with what
the
strategic objectives are now i'm also
talking about
if someone is in a position where being
responsible for the strategic objectives
is their role
if i have a job at a company i might not
do any of this stuff that i'm talking
about
because someone else might be setting
strategic objectives and i'm
focused on doing a really great job
executing um
i think that's actually one of the
problems is so many of the
not all of but a lot of the kind of
current productivity
tip books were written by entrepreneurs
and then everybody has like some
assumption that being an entrepreneur is
a better thing and i actually think for
most people having a job is better than
being an entrepreneur
because being able to
stop work at a certain point and not
being responsible for everybody's
payroll
and all like that but just being able to
go and do good work towards an
organization they believe in like is
awesome
um and for most people figuring out how
to be responsible for the outcome of the
project and everybody's payroll and like
that is just
stressful in a way that is typologically
not fit
um so i think it's important to not have
this idea that
everybody should be an entrepreneur or
like if you're reading
robert greene the idea that everyone
should be a general like it just life
doesn't
work that way it's not supposed to work
that way so there's different
there's different tips based on the type
of
role that you'd be in for productivity
um
and honestly the most effective thing i
have found for my own productivity by
far
is having someone good at it help me
with it regularly
um so
it's kind of like why some people who
are bodybuilders still take a trainer to
the gym
or at least a workout partner that's
focused on the thing with them is not
necessarily that they're missing the
knowledge or the fundamental capability
but if i'm wanting to go to failure in
my sets
then all of my attention and energy is
in that
rather than paying attention to how many
seconds i was in time under tension and
if that's progressing from the way it
was previously
and how many seconds between this set
and the next set
so having someone else hold the context
so that i can be all the way in on
the process like anytime someone wants
to go all the way in that
that decreases their need for task
switching between different types of
cognitive functions
so this is where having the right kind
of executive assistant or
um chief of staff or somebody like that
if someone is in one of those positions
can be
enormously helpful so um
when when i have someone who knows what
my strategic objectives are and is
holding all of the inbound requests and
all the things that i'm saying i'm
wanting to do they're holding and
organizing
the whole gtd thing and then checking
me to make sure that it's optimized that
means that i i get to stay
in the optimization i get to stay in
doing the optimized tasks
outside of the time that i'm doing
strategic planning not continuously
moving back and re-redoing organization
and honestly with all of the
organizational
tools i learned nothing was as effective
as having someone's help
awesome all right so uh we'll
end with one more question uh it's a
juicy one uh evan and amber
you're up uh you're gonna meet yourself
hey um so my question and i wrote it as
the top three but feel free to change
the number
um given the time and and where you want
to go with it so i
i'm wondering so what questions
do you have right now daniel which um
you a believe are answerable
and not just by some super intelligence
or something but practically speaking
um and uh you don't know the answer to
these right now
and you think would be most valuable to
you
or yeah to say to you personally to know
the answers to these things
there's a set of questions that are more
theoretical
and then there's a set of questions that
are more
tactical
i'm very much actively asking questions
around
things about
faster processes for being able to help
certain types of human development at
scale
people's development in their epistemics
in their emotional maturity in their
interpersonal skills
um and what is the what are the upper
bounds of how effectively we can do that
what percentage of the population
needs to have what amount of
developments
within what different types of
governance systems to
to be effective
what love what type of development can
we
what is the kind of gaussian
distribution on human development in
different ways that we can expect from
raising humans differently different
models of kind of how we could
do development at a at a longer term
civilization scale
i have a lot of questions in the space
right now
um
that are more kind of theoretical in
terms of more
tactical things um
working on for the this
kind of sense making
project um consilience project
is going to have
sense making content it puts out but
it's more focused on how does it
actually facilitate a cultural movement
towards better quality sense making
better quality
dialogue so that our capacity for
problem solving together actually
emerges
and the so the products we put out the
kind of news and the kind of meta news
analysis
is actually to be an attractor for
people to
come to where there's better more
innocence making but also to be a place
where we're doing
open source prototyping of what it could
be
and encouraging people to copy it and
innovate and utilize these things
because we're gonna the project's gonna
have a five-year time to live
and so its goal is to catalyze basically
to take care of stewarding the
information commons and the epistemic
commons while trying to catalyze
the commons to steward itself um
through a number of things a number of
different ways of doing that so
uh how so how
how we best do the kind of innovation
prize and innovation environment
what the categories of the innovation
prizes would be and
how we bring together the right sources
of capital
the right sources of distribution with
the right projects and the right talent
to be able to facilitate
um everything from the best projects
in civics education for high school
students to the best
projects in creating web browser plugins
that automatically fact check and look
for layoff frames to the best projects
that
correct bias in journalism or peer
review like all of those that are part
of the
info and episemic commons so how do we
facilitate the movement
how do we design the prize how do we
design the forums such
that the best sense making and the best
good faith dialogue are what
emerge um
and how do we engender the most
effective types of
collaboration and not the dysfunctional
types of competition in that environment
these are probably some of the questions
that i'm focused on having good
tangible answers quickly too
any follow-up uh evan
no thank you that was wonderful
beautiful
all right so uh we're gonna wrap it up
now um before i
close out daniel any kind of closing
thoughts anything you like to
summarize or anything that came alive
today
yeah i think um
the question of are we addressing more
personal
philosophy psychology topics or systemic
topics
maybe you have some way of getting
people's input on what they are
seeking and what is useful i don't know
if this is useful and i don't
want to make a poor use of anyone's time
um
and so before the next one i would
i actually have this is an interesting
thing about convening
i have a very strong value around giving
people good
calibrated expectations when inviting
them to something of what the thing is
so
as a way of respecting their choice is
this a thing i want to come to and put
my time into or not
so i wonder if we can clarify
what people would really find useful and
then clarify
what our intent is so they can come or
not based on whether or not that
resonates
that i would like that cool cool
yeah um i'll do that i think i'll
probably do a survey or something after
i launch this video
um on my mailing list and see see what
happens and the frame is
digital porch so it's like it's
open-ended thing that we can kind of
firm it up for the next session um so
that being said
daniel thanks so much for coming to the
stoat today everyone thanks
for coming um a couple announcements
before i close out
actually i'll take in tyson right now uh
tyson uh so we're having a rap on
battles event
on the same link right after this in
about like a couple of minutes
uh so tyson could you uh plug that
yes thank you peter thank you daniel
this is awesome and i look forward to
the next couple
so rap unbattles we are practicing
freestyle spoken word and rap so we play
some beats
and we talk with one another to practice
sharpening our thinking challenging one
another's
ideas and beliefs and ways of thinking
and engaging
in some good faith dialectic through
freestyle
and so the beats and the freestyle sort
of forces us to speak
into unknowingness and not prepare what
we're going to say and
practice getting into that group flow
together last week was
a lot of fun like i had a really good
time so
i look forward to seeing many of you
there you can participate or come
prepared for
unbattle the choice is yours but no
previous experience is required
so see you soon thank you tyson uh
and we're launching a new series at the
stoa called communitas club
um margaret uh and i are gonna uh run it
uh and it starts tomorrow and margaret
do you wanna um
unmute and just kind of give it a plug
and give people an understanding what to
expect
uh sure so we're hoping to
create a space where we can explore
different
relational and intersubjective
modalities um and kind of
create a bridge between propositional
and participatory learning
so tomorrow to set your expectations in
case you
don't want to attend um it's gonna be
more of a design session to kind of hear
what's
alive for the community of the stoa and
what people are interested in focusing
on
and to get your ideas about how to
structure sessions in a way that will
give the most to the community so um
tomorrow 5 30 come share your opinions
thoughts
all are welcome beautiful and we're
going to look at different modalities
like circling uh
non-violent communication uh verbal
aikido
um reflective structure dialogue force
landers even kind of come in to do his
femoral group process uh the idea is
just to kind of like
talk about it test it out and maybe port
it into the stowe's wisdom gym and kind
of
create some bespoke psycho technologies
um so that being said
uh you can go rsvp to everything on the
website the stoa.ca
you can also check out our patreon uh
and
our sub stack um that being said
everyone
thank you so much for coming to the
store today and just hold on tight
we'll play some music and then i'll take
entice in a moment